A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Africa and the Middle East, Johannesburg, South Africa Office Files FA509
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Africa and the Middle East, Johannesburg, South Africa Office Files
1989-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA509
1 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access note
Material is open for scholarly research, with prior archival review.
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Office files of the Africa and Middle East Program in South Africa.
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series: 1. International Agencies and Donors. 2. Manica Province. 3. Organizations.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation’s future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford’s international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee’s report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation’s aspiration‎al goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
- International Agencies and Donors, I
  - CIMA, 1995; Photos/Film (Box 1)
  - Christian Care, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Churches, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - EBANO, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Mozambique Justice Visit, 1996 (Box 1)
  - University of Rio de Janeiro, 1993-1996 (Box 1)
- Manica Province, II
  - Centro de Estudios Internacionales, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Paul Richards -- Understanding War Conference, 1993 (Box 2)
- Organizations, III
  - African Studies in the United States, 1989-1996 (Box 2)
  - South African Universities, 1994 (Box 2)